<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>shiny | Brenwin&#39;s blog for Data Stories</title>
    <link>/tag/shiny/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/shiny/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>shiny</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>shiny</title>
      <link>/tag/shiny/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>covid-19 Seasonality Shiny App </title>
      <link>/post/covid-19-seasonality-shiny-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/covid-19-seasonality-shiny-app/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;720&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; src=&#34;../data/shinyguide.mp4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THe code to the app can be found in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/etc5523-2020/shiny-assessment-brenwin1&#34;&gt;github link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;about-shiny-app&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;About Shiny App&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I created a Shiny App to assess the novel coronavirus’ seasonality. This app was created as part of my unit (ETC5523 Communicating with Data) assessment but also seeks to provide insights of the novel coronavirus seasonality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation of this app comes amid many speculations especially from health experts around the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2020/04/21/coronavirus-secondwave-cdcdirector/&#34;&gt;increased risk of virus spreading in colder seasons&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Sun (2020)&lt;/span&gt;) Here in Melbourne, we &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloombergquint.com/coronavirus-outbreak/melbourne-is-living-the-cold-weather-virus-surge-experts-fear&#34;&gt;experienced virus resurgence in winter that dwarfed the 1st outbreak in March&lt;/a&gt;. As Europe eased restrictions, for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/09/02/coronavirus-and-winter-health-experts-wary-about-a-possible-new-wave.html&#34;&gt;first time ever, they reported higher number of cases than USA&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Meredith (2020)&lt;/span&gt;) Besides, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/health-53515077&#34;&gt;many respiratory viruses have a seasonality component&lt;/a&gt; that peak in winter (for example people are more prone to flu in winter) as they tend to be more active among other reasons. (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Gallagher (2020)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As colder seasons migrate to the Northern hemisphere, we take this opportunity to consolidate what we have learnt from countries in the Southern Hemisphere to potentially anticipate what could happen to the countries in the Northern Hemisphere as many countries seek to reopen their economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confounding variables that add to the virus’ level of risk must also be taken into account. Hence tropical countries are included as “baseline” for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;self-review&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Self-Review&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-i-think-was-done-well&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I think was done well&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;planning-exploratory-data-analysis&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Planning &amp;amp; Exploratory Data Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the planning phase was thorough and significantly improved efficiency of making the app. A lot of thought was put into making an app that is useful and relevant with the current situation. I think the planning phase is crucial before any execution could even begin and this is where &lt;strong&gt;exploratory Data analysis&lt;/strong&gt; came into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I had to look around data (luckily I have gone through some covid-19 data before *see previous blog posts) and asked: what could be done &amp;amp; what would I want to see. Lucky for me, I remembered stumbling upon a twitter post awhile back that showed Europe having more cases than USA for the first time *unfortunately lost the post since. So it gave me the idea start with. So I looked more about the topic and read articles relating to virus’ seasonality and also look at other apps out there for inspiration. Hence led me to thinking that an app that specifically examines virus’ seasonality would be useful and different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially being relatively new to &lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt;, I understood that I need to come up with an elaborate plan within my capabilities, knowledge and time frame. Although I had to look through my notes and lectures, counterintuitively, I think having a sufficiently elaborate plan enabled efficiency in execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;layout-of-the-app&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layout of the app&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the usual &lt;code&gt;fludPage&lt;/code&gt; set up, &lt;code&gt;navbarPage&lt;/code&gt; was used. The enabled the app’s layout to be highly customisable as it allowed each &lt;code&gt;tabPanel&lt;/code&gt; to exist as a page on its own&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tab 1, &lt;code&gt;fluidRow&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;column&lt;/code&gt; were employed to set aside grid space to position each of the identical elements in a neat manner. The plots were vertically aligned to facilitate comparison of countries in Tropics, Northern &amp;amp; Southern Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tab 2, the advantage of &lt;code&gt;navbarPage&lt;/code&gt; was utilized. With a &lt;code&gt;sidebarLayout&lt;/code&gt;, after the &lt;code&gt;sideBarPanel&lt;/code&gt; was in place, the map can be plotted to fill the entire page in the &lt;code&gt;mainPanel&lt;/code&gt;. This enabled users to view the map and its corresponding plots side by side for easy comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, Shiny’s &lt;code&gt;tags$list&lt;/code&gt; was applied extensively to configure the text on the app.
These functions recreate &lt;code&gt;html tags&lt;/code&gt; under the hood. This was useful for someone who is more
comfortable in using R code than raw html code. After all, Shiny is a html web page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;functionality&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Functionality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This app was created to optimize its functionality reflected in its layout, contents and reactivity components. Comparing within country (Tab 2) provides a understand the case in hand (covid’s Seasonality). It has blue shaded rectangles indicating winter months. The scales were set free as
the main point of this tab was to compare each country’s (at different hemisphere) trend in the different seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparing across countries (Tab 3), I acknowledged that many variables come into play.
One of it was population. Hence, the reactivity component allowed users to toggle
between indicators (one of raw count and the other per 100,000 population). Again,
to be able to compare counts in each season, the user must be able to set a date range. Lastly,
a &lt;code&gt;data table&lt;/code&gt; was embedded including a lockdown variable as I think lockdown is a big factor
in differentiating the case counts of countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to add that putting a “Show” &lt;code&gt;ActionButton&lt;/code&gt; to update the map was useful so
to avoid users having to load the map each time a country is added to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-can-be-improved&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What can be improved&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the interface of the app could be improved to make the app more appealing and welcoming. Even though the creative juices may be running, many of the times I need to consider its feasibility especially given the limited time. For example, using &lt;code&gt;css&lt;/code&gt; to style the web page with icons, fancier fonts etc. would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would say the map could be improved. A “click-to-show” instead of hovering over the points may be a better user interface. In hindsight, using &lt;code&gt;leaflet&lt;/code&gt; map could have been a better option with its zooming in and out feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I was unable to deploy the app in &lt;code&gt;shinyapps.io&lt;/code&gt; as the data set was too big and free users are only entitled to instance size of 1GB. A workaround this this may be to use leaflet to significantly cull the data (by separating &lt;code&gt;world&lt;/code&gt; map data and coronavirus &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; instead of putting them together).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I believe that the interactive elements could also be better. For example, connecting the different plots to map by clicks. I also thought of hovering over number of cases (fill bar) which interacts with the map to show the number of countries hitting that threshold would be neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, &lt;strong&gt;animating&lt;/strong&gt; the map to see the different number of cases (with fill colour changing according to a metric e.g. number of cases) over time; in a date range specified by the user would be very interesting and helpful to examine the covid’s seasonality. Will try to do these in the near future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-can-be-improved-limited-by-datatechnology&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What can be improved (limited by data/technology)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding coronavirus data on covid-19 across the world, issues around discrepancy in data collection methods and rules would cause comparability problems. For example, countries may have different testing rates, delays in reporting, lockdown measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the lag in loading speed might be a hindrance when it comes to doing an analysis. Increasing the internet speed would certainly improve the app’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking on a country on the map provides a walkthrough of latest relevant news on covid a country and a brief summary of its latest happenings (could be a little far fetched).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;software-references&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Software References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these are done using &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; software using &lt;code&gt;Hugo Blogdown&lt;/code&gt; template&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including these &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages were referenced:&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;code&gt;Shiny&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Chang et al. (2020)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;code&gt;DT&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Xie, Cheng, and Tan (2020)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;code&gt;leaflet&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Cheng, Karambelkar, and Xie (2019)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Wickham et al. (2019)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level1 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references hanging-indent&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Rshiny&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chang, Winston, Joe Cheng, JJ Allaire, Yihui Xie, and Jonathan McPherson. 2020. &lt;em&gt;Shiny: Web Application Framework for R&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Rleaflet&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheng, Joe, Bhaskar Karambelkar, and Yihui Xie. 2019. &lt;em&gt;Leaflet: Create Interactive Web Maps with the Javascript ’Leaflet’ Library&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=leaflet&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=leaflet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-bbc-winter&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gallagher, James. 2020. “Coronavirus: How Bad Will Winter Really Be?” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/health-53515077&#34;&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/health-53515077&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-cnbc&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meredith, Sam. 2020. “Health Experts Sound the Alarm on a Possible New Coronavirus Wave This Winter.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/09/02/coronavirus-and-winter-health-experts-wary-about-a-possible-new-wave.html&#34;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/09/02/coronavirus-and-winter-health-experts-wary-about-a-possible-new-wave.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-wash-post&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sun, Lena. 2020. “CDC Director Warns Second Wave of Coronavirus Is Likely to Be Even More Devastating.” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2020/04/21/coronavirus-secondwave-cdcdirector/&#34;&gt;https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2020/04/21/coronavirus-secondwave-cdcdirector/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Rtidyverse&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wickham, Hadley, Mara Averick, Jennifer Bryan, Winston Chang, Lucy D’Agostino McGowan, Romain François, Garrett Grolemund, et al. 2019. “Welcome to the tidyverse.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Open Source Software&lt;/em&gt; 4 (43): 1686. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01686&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01686&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Rdt&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xie, Yihui, Joe Cheng, and Xianying Tan. 2020. &lt;em&gt;DT: A Wrapper of the Javascript Library ’Datatables’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=DT&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=DT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
